<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exact journal of the victorious progress of their majesties forces under the command of Gen. Ginckle, this summer in Ireland giving a particular account of the several skirmishes, battles, sieges and surrenders of Athlone, Galloway, Slego, &amp;c. : together, with the total defeat of the Irish at Agrim and Thomond-Bridge : and lastly, of the capitulation and surrender of Limerick.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38926</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3651</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20484</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11773604</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11773604</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48905</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38926)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48905)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 530:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exact journal of the victorious progress of their majesties forces under the command of Gen. Ginckle, this summer in Ireland giving a particular account of the several skirmishes, battles, sieges and surrenders of Athlone, Galloway, Slego, &amp;c. : together, with the total defeat of the Irish at Agrim and Thomond-Bridge : and lastly, of the capitulation and surrender of Limerick.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Randolph Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Reede-Ginckel, Godard, --  Baron van, 1644-1703.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1688-1689.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48905:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48905:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXACT JOURNAL OF THE Victorious PROGRESS OF THEIR Majeſties Forces Under the COMMAND of Gen. Ginckle, This SUMMER in IRELAND: GIVING A Particular ACCOUNT of the <hi>Several <hi>Skirmiſhes, Battles, Sieges</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Surrenders</hi> of ATHLONE, GALLOWAY, SLEGO, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TOGETHER, With the <hi>Total</hi> DEFEAT of the IRISH at <hi>Agrim</hi> and <hi>Thomond-Bridge:</hi> And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> of the <hi>Capitulation</hi> and <hi>Surrender</hi> of LIMERICK.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Randolph Taylor</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> MDCXCI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:48905:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48905:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>'TIS well known, that Ireland was conquer'd at firſt by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and bad been all along un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the eaſie Yoke of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> till <hi>James</hi> II. aſcended the Throne. But he, by a Policy, contrary to all the World, deſigning to ſubdue <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to Popery and <hi>French</hi> Government, endeavour'd all he could to have made <hi>Ireland</hi> in her Turn the Inſtrument of that prepoſterous Conqueſt. To which purpoſe, he made uſe of the general Inclination of that People to the Romiſh Religion, ſent for whole Regiments of that Nation into <hi>England,</hi> bred 'em up both for. Officers and Souldiers, with no leſs Care than the Turks do their <hi>Janizaries;</hi> and when he had fill'd all {iIre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land} with expert Warriors, deliver'd up the whole Power of the Government into the hands of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks; ſo that all that part of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarchy was only tackt to <hi>England,</hi> by the ſingle Thread of Papiſtical Obedience, during a Catholick Reign. After which, King <hi>James</hi> himſelf, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving abdicated <hi>England,</hi> headed a general Revolt of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> from the Imperial Crown of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> which had only left ſubordinate to it the City of <hi>London-Derry,</hi> and one Corner of <hi>Ulſter.</hi> So that ſo fair a Portion of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Dominion, ſo Convenient for ſpacious <hi>Harbors,</hi> ſo fertile for the Soil, ſo abounding in all Things for the ſupport of humane Life, and ſo particularly famous for admitting no venomous Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to live in it, but only Prieſts and Jeſuits, was either to be quite loſt, or quite to be re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>conquer'd.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:48905:3"/>
            <p>Therefore while the late King <hi>James,</hi> aſſiſted with <hi>French</hi> Succours, commanded all things, and had ſet the forfeited Crown of <hi>Irleand</hi> upon his <hi>Head,</hi> Duke <hi>Schomberg</hi> was by King <hi>William</hi> ſent to ſtop the Career of the abdicated Prince, and his abominated Crew of <hi>Gallick</hi> Foreigners. And firſt of all the Duke, like the Roman <hi>Fabius, Cunctando reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit rem.</hi> Next King <hi>William</hi> in Perſon, like the far-fam'd <hi>Scipio,</hi> forc'd the defeated Invader to abandon the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. And now, lastly, this Campaign, and ſecond <hi>Summer</hi> from the Contest begun, you ſee the threatning War concluded, while the renowned <hi>Ginckle,</hi> like a Torrent, ſweeps all before him, and after his having broken the Enemy in Battle, ſtript 'em of all their ſtrong <hi>Holds</hi> by ſtorm, or conſtrain'd 'em to ſurrender, and ſcatter'd the Fugitives to ſtarve among the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, leaves no part of the whole Kingdom unreduced under the Obedience of her lawful Sovereigns. Atchievments not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by Number, but by Courage and Conduct, and meriting large <hi>Encomiums,</hi> beyond the narrow Limits of a Preface.</p>
            <p>And now I would fain know what are become of thoſe brisk <hi>Jacobites,</hi> who thought a languiſhing <hi>French</hi> Cauſe could be ſupported by laying malicious and extravagant Wagers. Where-e'er they are, they have nothing now to do, but to pay their loſt Money, and, with <hi>Hudibraſs,</hi> conclude, That Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are Fools Arguments. And indeed, 'tis pity, they do not live at this time in <hi>France,</hi> where the King is ſetting ſo many Projects on foot to raiſe Money. For their Names would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be taken, to inform the King where the Men of Money liv'd. And then he preſently ſends his Officers for ſuch a <hi>Sum</hi> to be re-paid <hi>ad Graecas Kalendas.</hi> I only tell'ent the <hi>Story;</hi> let them pick out the <hi>Inference</hi> themſelves.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48905:3"/>
            <head>AN EXACT JOURNAL OF THE Victorious Progreſs of Their <hi>Majeſties Forces</hi> this <hi>Summer</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>HIS Majeſty, King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> III. by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous Succeſs of his Arms at the <hi>Boyn</hi> the laſt Year, was in a very ſhort time become Maſter of the greateſt patt of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and had driven the late King <hi>James</hi> quite out of the Kingdom; but the Seaſon of the Year, and the exceſſive Rains, ſo frequent in that Country, would not permit him any farther Action. For which reaſon, after he had given order for his Forces to take up their Winter-Quarters in ſuch a Manner, as to ſhut up the Rebels within the moſt narrow limits that might be, and prevent their Incurſions into the regain'd Countries, His Majeſty returned for <hi>England;</hi> leaving to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Army and compleat his Conqueſts, General <hi>Ginkle,</hi> a Perſon of great Experience, Fidelity, Conduct and Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as will appear by the enſuing Journal. So that if Story receive its luſtre from the Grandeur of the Actions which it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, perhaps this Journal may be thought as conſiderable as has for many years come forth; as well for the Courage of the Souldiers, the Difficulty and Succeſs of their Euterprizes, and the Importance of their Conqueſts.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48905:4"/>During the <hi>Winter,</hi> Both ſides lay quiet, but the very Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of Spring warm'd the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to Action, which tho' not ſo conſiderable, yet was preparatory to facilitate the Opening of the grand Campaign, which did not begin till ſometime after. For upon the <hi>14th.</hi> of <hi>March</hi> (where this Journal begins) Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Lillington,</hi> between eight and nine at Night, march'd from <hi>Roſcreagh,</hi> with a Party of his own, which being joyn'd by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from <hi>Bix,</hi> made up together Three Hundred Horſe, Foot and Dragoons, and advanc'd toward <hi>Nagah;</hi> but finding the way to be longer then he expected, and day coming on, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tach'd Eighteen Horſe and as many Foot, which he mounted upon <hi>Garrans,</hi> and made all the haſte he could to ſecure the Bridge about half a Mile from <hi>Nenagh.</hi> Upon which the whole Garriſon ſallied out, to oppoſe him: However with that ſmall party he maintain'd the Paſs, till his Foot came up; and then leaving them at the Bridge, he advanc'd with his Horſe toward the Enemy, who at a diſtance were very free of their Shot, but ſo ſoon as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> came nere them, began to run: upon which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> purſu'd them, and kill'd about Twenty, of which number was a Lieutenant, and took one Cornet. This done, the Colonel ſent a Detachment to ſecure the Paſs on the other ſide of <hi>Nenagh,</hi> towards <hi>Limerick,</hi> while the reſt of his Men entered the Town (the Rebels flying into the Caſtle) and burnt all the Houſes, together with a great Quantity of Malt and Mcal, and brought away three hundred Head of black Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, with the Loſs but of two Men ſlain out-right, and another wounded; but of the Rebels were kill'd between forty and fifty.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time News came from <hi>Cork,</hi> that upon advice that a Party of the Rebels were come before <hi>Ballimagoolis,</hi> a fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier Garriſon poſſeſs'd by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in that County, a Party was ſent from <hi>Cork</hi> to relieve it, of which the Enemy being inform'd, they drew off in great diſorder; whereupon the Garriſon ſallied out, kill['d ſeveral of the Enemy, and took ſever Priſoners.</p>
            <p>Upon the 15th of <hi>March</hi> a detach'd Party or 150 Dragoons, 100 Militia-Horſe, and 130 Foot, marched from <hi>Cork</hi> under the Command of Major <hi>Culliford,</hi> toward <hi>Ballyclongh,</hi> where the Rebels were about to have entrench'd themſelves; but upon the appearing of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> they quitted their Works, and fled with that haſte, that all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> could do in the purſuit was,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48905:4"/>to take ſeven Priſoners, of which four were Officers. With better ſucceſs a Party of Sir <hi>David Collier</hi>'s Regiment, quartered about <hi>Bandon,</hi> together with ſome of the <hi>Militia</hi> of that Place, 300 in all, Commanded by Lieutenant Colonel <hi>George Hamilton,</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at the ſame time into the Enemies Quarters about <hi>Bantry,</hi> where they killed above ſeventy of the Rebels, took fifteen Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſix hundred Head of Black Cattel, and a good number of Horſes, without the loſs of one Man.</p>
            <p>Of this Action, ſoon after there came a more full account: That upon notice that Brigadier <hi>Caroll</hi> had a deſign to ſend five Companies of Foot, with ſome Ammunition, to joyn Collonel <hi>O Donavan,</hi> in order to maintain <hi>Bantry,</hi> and put the Country under Contribution; Lieut. Coll. <hi>Hamilton</hi> marched on the 15th of <hi>March,</hi> with 200 Foot of Sir <hi>David Colliers</hi> Regiment, 60 Horſe commanded by Lieut. Coll. <hi>Ogilby,</hi> and 80 of the Militia, and the next day about two in the Afternoon, came in ſight of <hi>Bantry;</hi> but finding that the Enemy had quitted the Place the ſame Morning, followed them with all the expedition he could. Whereupon the Enemy, perceiving themſelves ſo cloſely pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, left all their Cattel behind, and betook themſelves into the Bogs; however the <hi>Engliſh</hi> followed 'em four Miles, kill'd about 40, took 14 Priſoners, Coll. <hi>Courcy</hi> narrowly eſcaping, and brought off 1500 Head of Black Cattel, leaving ſeveral thouſands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, for want of People to drive 'em, That night the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſtay'd at <hi>Bantry;</hi> and the next day, after they had burnt the Town, returned back. In their way, the Enemy had laid 600 Men in Ambuſh, about ſix Miles from <hi>Bantry;</hi> but being diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the Vantcurriers of the Party, after one Volly they ran away to their Hills and Bogs, whither the <hi>Engliſh</hi> could not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuc them</p>
            <p>
               <hi>March</hi> 25. Thirty of the Militia-Dragoons, commanded by Lieutenant <hi>Powel,</hi> were ordered to fetch up ſeveral Perſons out of the County of <hi>Meath,</hi> who were ſuſpected to have been concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Murther of Coll. <hi>Foulks</hi>'s Souldiers; but in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, he had notice that a Party of Rapparees way-laid him not far from <hi>Hackets</hi>-Town, with a Reſolution to reſcue the Priſoners: Upon which, he ſent away ſeventeen of his Dragoons with the Priſoners, and with the other thirteen marched to <hi>Hackets</hi>-Town; where ſending for the Conſtable, after ſome hard threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48905:5"/>Words, the Conſtable inform'd him where the Rapparees lay; and then he immediately march'd to find 'em out. So ſoon as he approached the Place, he advanced with four of his Men into a Field adjoyning, where he fell in with a Party of twenty eight <hi>Iriſh,</hi> commanded by Captain <hi>O Neale.</hi> The Enemy ſeeing ſo ſmall a number, came up and fired at 'em, but without doing any hurt to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who anſwer'd them in the ſame Element to better purpoſe, killing two of the Rebels, and wounding <hi>O Neale</hi> himſelf. By which time, the reſt of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> being come in, charged the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and kill'd four of them, put the reſt to flight, and purſued them from place to place, till they had killed about twenty of them, and among the reſt their Captain <hi>O Neale;</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wounded before, was now perfectly cured; his Enemies becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Surgeons. Of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> only three were wounded, and two Horſes kill'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>March</hi> 27. Captain <hi>Mark Baggot,</hi> who came as a Spy from <hi>Limerick,</hi> and was taken in Womens Apparel, was try'd, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenc'd by a Court-Martial; but his Execution was reſpited, upon his offering to make ſome diſcovery. However, it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing afterwards that he did but dally with Juſtice, and that all his pretended Diſcoveries were of no moment, he was hang'd out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right upon the Twentieth of <hi>May</hi> following. At the concluſion of this Month, a Proclamation was publiſhed in <hi>Dublin,</hi> bearing Date <hi>March</hi> 26. purporting,</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">That notwithſtanding the great Clemency extended by their Majeſties to the Popiſh, <hi>Iriſh,</hi> whereby upon their ſubmiſſion they have had equal protection with their Proteſtant Subjects, yet ſuch was the inveterate Malice of many, that upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions they not only relieved their Majeſties Enemies, but joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them in committing and concealing many horrid Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, one of which of eight Souldiers inhumanly ſtrangled at one time, and in one place, was lately diſcovered, to have been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrated by the Inhabitants of the Place where the Souldiers were quartered, for which ſome of the Criminals had receiv'd juſt Puniſhment: And the Lords Juſtices-being fully ſatisfied that ſuch Offences could not be committed without the help or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance of the Protected Inhabitants; and having received In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation that there was a Confederacy among them to relieve their Majeſties Enemies, and to take all Opportunities to deſtroy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48905:5"/>their Officers and Souldiers; their Lordſhips therefore declar'd, That if any ſuch Murthers be hereafter committed, and the Inhabitants do not uſe their utmoſt endeavours to apprehend the Malefactors, that they ſhall be put out of their Majeſties protection, and be proceeded againſt as Spies and Enemies, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the courſe of War.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 2. Coll. <hi>Tiffin</hi> ſent out from <hi>Ballyſhannon</hi> a Party of two hundred Foot, and two Troops of Coll. <hi>Winns</hi> Dragoons, who marched within three Miles of <hi>Slego,</hi> where they kill'd thirty two of Captain <hi>Mackſherry</hi>'s Men, and took nine, and brought away with them a Booty of 180 Cows, 50 Sheep, and 30 Horſes; but the Captain with the reſt made their Eſcapes to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 4. A Party of <hi>Longford</hi> Gariſon, meeting with ſome of the Enemies Dragoons neear the River <hi>Enye,</hi> ſlew ſix; upon which, the reſt taking the River where it was not fordable, ten more of them were drown'd: Such a ſtrange thing is Fear, that it makes many Men run from one Death to another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 5. A ſmall Party of Dragoons, commanded by Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Maſter <hi>Topham,</hi> met with a detach'd Party of the Rebels, under the Command of Captain <hi>Bourke;</hi> of which they ſlew five, and an Enſign, the reſt betaking themſelves to their heels.</p>
            <p>The ſame day Brigadier <hi>Stewart</hi> ſent from <hi>Belturbat</hi> a Detach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of fifty Foot and twenty Dragoons, under the Command of Captain <hi>Stewart,</hi> with Orders to march toward <hi>Mohil,</hi> to free the Country from the <hi>Rapparees.</hi> The next morning, by break of day, being come within a Mile of the Place, they diſcover'd two Troops of the Enemies Dragoons, and about fifty Foot, that were guarding ſome <hi>Kereights;</hi> upon which, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſee to work with them, without any Preambles; but the Rebels, after the firſt firing, quitted their Horſes, and betook themſelves to the Woods and Bogs, whither the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Foot purſuing them, made a ſhift to kill thirty, and take five Priſoners: Which done, the Victors return'd to their Quarters, without any manner of Loſs, bringing along with them about an hundred Head of Black Cattel, and between ſixty and ſeventy Horſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 6. Quarter-Maſter <hi>Topham,</hi> with eighteen Dragoons and twelve Foot-Souldiers mounted upon <hi>Garrans,</hi> ſurpriz'd the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Guards near <hi>Newsaſtle,</hi> killed ſeventeen, and brought away
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48905:6"/>nine Priſoners, ſeven of which being found to be <hi>Rapparees,</hi> were immediately hang'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 7. Fifteen hundred of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army came before <hi>Iniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keam,</hi> and attackt the Garriſon of that Place, conſiſting of no more than forty four Men, commanded by Enſign <hi>Lindſay</hi> and Enſign <hi>Dalyel;</hi> but notwithſtanding ſo great a multitude of the Rebels, a part of that ſmall Garriſon defended the two Avenues to the Town above two Hours, till ſome of the Popiſh Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants treacherouſly gave the Enemy entrance into the Town through a by-way, and then the <hi>Engliſh</hi> retreated to the main Guard, which they maintain'd ſix Hours longer, at what time the Rebels ſummoned the Defendants to ſurrender; and upon their refuſal, had brought together ſeveral Hundreds of Faggots to fire the Guard-Houſe; when in the very nick of Opportnnity, Collonel <hi>Ogilby,</hi> with a Party of Horſe and Foot, came to their Relief; upon whoſe approach, the Enemy drew off in confuſion; which the Garriſon perceiving, ſallied out upon the Rebels, and kill'd about fifty, with no more than the loſs of one Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 9. Some of Captain <hi>Green</hi>'s Militia-Dragoons, marching into the Enemies Quarters, kill'd ſeveral of the <hi>Rapparees,</hi> and laid in Aſhes a Village that gave them harbor. The ſame day alſo a Court-Martial was held, where Brigadier <hi>Stewart</hi> preſided, and where ſeveral Perſons, who upon their Tryals appear'd to be Spies, and ſuch as had aſſiſted and ſheltered the <hi>Rapparees,</hi> were ſentenced to be hanged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 13. Quarter-Maſter <hi>Callaghan</hi> went out with a Party, and in a ſhort time after, return'd with eleven Priſoners, twelve Horſes, and ſeventy Head of Black Cattel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 18. General <hi>Ginkle</hi> arrived at <hi>Dublin,</hi> whither moſt of the General Officers repaired at the ſame time, to conſult with the Lords Juſtices about the Affairs of the Campaign, and haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their Majeſties Forces to take the Field; which he was the more encourag'd to do, in regard that the <hi>Monmouth</hi> Yacht had already brought Money for the Army, and that ſeveral other Ships were arrived at <hi>Cork, Waterford,</hi> and <hi>Kingſale,</hi> with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruits both of Horſe and Foot, of which two thouſand were by that time come to <hi>Dublin,</hi> where, through the great Care and Diligence of the General, the Train of Artillery, with the Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons and Carriages lay all ready fitted.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:48905:6"/>
            <p>Much about the ſame time was publiſhed a Proclamation for the apprehending and ſecuring <hi>Chriſtopher Brown</hi> a Romiſh Prieſt, who by the Examinations of ſeveral Perſons, appeared to be, if no the firſt Contriver, and principal Directer, yet a main Abetter and Incourager of the Murther of many of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Souldiers, in <hi>Mallahudder</hi>'s Church; and propoſing a Reward of Fifty Pounds for any Perſon that ſhould ſeize him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 19. No leſs than ſeven hundred of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſtanding-Army attackt a Stone-Houſe, called <hi>Croghan,</hi> near <hi>Philipſtown,</hi> and valiantly took a Corporal and ſix common Souldiers, after they had with much more Bravery defended themſelves till all their Powder was ſpent, and that they had killed twelve of the Enemy.</p>
            <p>But this Loſs was reveng'd the ſame day with advantage; for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> being inform'd, that a conſiderable number of the Rebels were come near to <hi>Macromp,</hi> one of their Majeſties Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier Garriſons, a Party of eighty Horſe and an nundred and fifty Dragoons, of the Army, and as many of the Militia, was drawn out under the Command of Major <hi>Kirk.</hi> This Party marched the 19th in the Evening, and by break of day the next Morning came up with the Rebels, who preſently took to their Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in the Woods and Bogs, whither the <hi>Engliſh</hi> purſu'd them; and after a chace of ſome hours kill'd twenty, took five Priſoners, and brought off ſome Horſes and Cattel. Much about the ſame time the <hi>Rapparees</hi> coming with a ſtrong Party to <hi>Curraglaſs</hi> near <hi>Tallough,</hi> had ſtollen ſome Horſes belonging to Collonel <hi>Denopp</hi>'s Regiment, and ſurpriz'd four Troops. Upon which, the Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel gave preſent Orders for the taking up ſeveral of the <hi>Iriſh.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants about that place; declaring withal, That if they did not procure the Horſes and Men to be brought back by ſuch a certain day, they ſhould every one be hang'd: Which wrought ſo effectually upon the Priſoners, that both Men and Horſes were brought back, by the time appointed, to the place where they were taken; and for a further Attonement of the Injury done, ſome of the Fellows alſo, that had been Actors in the Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:48905:7"/>
            <p>At the ſame time three hundred <hi>Rapparees,</hi> lying in Ambu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> cade, not far from <hi>Kennegad,</hi> had ſeiz'd upon forty eight Sack of Meal, that were going thither with a very ſmall Guard that made their eſcapes; of which notice being given to the Town, a Party of the Garriſon fally'd out, recover'd a good part of the Meal, and kill'd ſeveral of the <hi>Rapparees,</hi> with their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 24. Captain <hi>Pallaſer,</hi> upon ſome intelligence that was given him of the <hi>Rapparees,</hi> march'd out with forty Fire-locks of the Army, and twenty of the Militia; but by the Treachery of one <hi>Terence Magragh,</hi> was drawn into an Ambuſh of no leſs than two of the Enemies Regiments of Foot and ſome Horſe: Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> got into the Ruins of an old Caſtle, where theleſs, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> got into the Ruins of an old Caſtle, where they vigoriouſly defended themſelves till all their Ammunition was ſpent; but then were forc'd to accept of Quarter, and were carried Priſoners to <hi>Nanagh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 27. The Earl of <hi>Meath</hi>'s, and the Lord <hi>Lisburn</hi>'s Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments arrived at <hi>Mullingar,</hi> and encamp'd without the Town. The ſame day one <hi>Walter Brown,</hi> formerly High Conſtable of the Barony of <hi>Delwyn,</hi> was hang'd for a Spy in the ſame Town. And upon the ſame 27th of <hi>April</hi> alſo it was, that five hundred of the Militia of the County of <hi>Dublin,</hi> marched out of that City to the Town of <hi>Kildare,</hi> where they joyn'd the Regiment of Horſe, commanded by Collonel <hi>Piper,</hi> and which were deſign'd to clear thoſe parts from the Robberies and Violences of the <hi>Rapparees.</hi> And the ſame day arriv'd in <hi>Dublin</hi> Road the Ships from <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> laden with the Stores for the Artillery and Ordnance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 28. Collonel <hi>Brewer,</hi> and Lieutenant-Collonel <hi>Hamilton,</hi> with ſix hundred Foot and twenty Horſe, marched into the Enemies Quarters beyond the Caſtle of <hi>Donere,</hi> between which place and <hi>Kilbegan,</hi> about two thouſand of the <hi>Rapparces</hi> had for ſome time ſhelter'd themſelves in Hutts and Cabins. But though at the firſt ſight of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> they drew up in a kind of Bravado, upon the Hills, in ſeveral Bodies of Horſe and Foot, yet upon the Collonels nearer approach, they flew to their Bogs and Woods, whither the <hi>Engliſh</hi> purſu'd them, kill'd about fifty, and after they had burnt a great number of their Hutts and Hovels, returned to their Quarters.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:48905:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 30. Capt. <hi>Clayton</hi> was ſent with a Party of Men, to relieve the Garriſon of <hi>Ballimagooly,</hi> where Capt. <hi>Hornycroſe</hi> then comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and was the ſame day to have march'd his Men to <hi>Cork,</hi> ſo ſoon as Captain <hi>Clayton</hi> had relieved him. But underſtanding that the Garriſon of <hi>Ballyclough</hi> had a deſign to intercept him, he thought it not convenient to march by day, and therefore ſet forward about 12 a Clock at Night. However, this was not ſo privately carried, but that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> had notice of it, and thereupon drew out a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and twenty of their beſt Horſe, and as many Dragoons, with two hundred and fifty Voluntiers and <hi>Rapparees,</hi> commanded by Brigadier <hi>Caroll,</hi> Sir <hi>James Cotter,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Kinſale,</hi> Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Laſly,</hi> Major <hi>Slingsby,</hi> Captain <hi>Coppinger</hi> and Captain <hi>Comb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> who fell upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> juſt on the other ſide of <hi>Six-mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water,</hi> about three of the Clock in the Morning. Upon their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> faced, and about twenty fired upon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſo well to the purpoſe, that they brake the Rebels Front, and put them into ſome diſorder; which gave the <hi>Engliſh</hi> a good opportunity to retreat to an old Pound that had a Mud-wall about it, breaſt-high, and to clap up a Truckle at the place where they entred. Whereupon the advanced Party of the Enemy, belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the day their own, boldly made up to the Pound, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the Captain and his Man Quarter; which he refuſing, they began a brisk Charge, and preſſed hard upon the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by whom the Rebels were ſo warmly received, that ſeveral of their Number were ſlain, and carried off, during the heat of the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: However, they made a ſecond and a third Attack, though with the ſame ill ſucceſs. And thus the Conflict laſted for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral hours, till notice of it being carried to <hi>Cork,</hi> a Party was forthwith ſent from thence to the Captain's relief; but the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my were all fled before they arrived, leaving dead upon the place Captain <hi>Coppinger</hi> and Caprain <hi>Combdon:</hi> Collonel <hi>Laſly</hi> and the Lord of <hi>Kinſale</hi> were likewiſe dangerouſly wounded, and carried off, and about fifty more wounded. Major <hi>Slingsby</hi> was brought dangerouſly wounded to <hi>Cork,</hi> where, in little hopes of Life, he was ſo ingenious as to confeſs, That he believed the Hand of <hi>God</hi> was againſt their Party, for that altlio' they offered and promiſed Quarter to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> yet had they yielded, they had reſolved to put them all to the Sword. Of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were loſt no more than eight Men out of fourſcore; but of the Enemy 'tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that more were kill'd and wounded than thoſe they fought againſt.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:48905:8"/>
            <p>At the beginning of <hi>May,</hi> the Lords Juſtices put forth a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, ſtrictly charging and commanding all Officers, Civil and Military, and all Souldiers of their Majeſties Army, not to moleſt any Sutlers that ſhould have a Warrant from the Lord Juſtices, the General of the Army, or Collonel of any Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to follow the Camp; nor to take any thing from the ſaid Sutlers, nor to uſe any violence towards them, upon pain of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeverely proceeded againſt: And that the Collonels ſhould take care that the Souldiers paid for every thing they had of the Sutlers, according to the ſetled Rates: And to prevent the Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries and Spoils committed upon the Country, by ſeveral unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Perſons that followed the Camp, they further ordered all their Majeſties Subjects, both Proteſtants and Papiſts, to ſtay at, or repair to, their ſeveral Habitations, for the Preſervation and Improvement of the ſame; and that no Perſons ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to follow the Camp, but ſuch as brought Proviſions to the Army, or upon ſome lawful occaſion approved by the General, or Commander in Chief.</p>
            <p>By another Proclamation, all the Inhabitants of the Counties of <hi>Waterford</hi> and <hi>Tipperary,</hi> were commanded to repair to their Places of Habitation, or the next Garriſon; and the Inhabitants of the Counties of <hi>Cork, Limerick,</hi> and <hi>Kerry,</hi> were ordered to do the ſame, in order to their being employed in the Militia, for the Defence of the Country, when their Army ſhould be drawn into the Field.</p>
            <p>And by an Order of General <hi>Ginkle,</hi> all Officers and Souldiers, and all other Perſons whatſoever, were ſtrictly commanded not to preſs any Horſes or Carts, without licenſe from himſelf in writing; nor to preſs any Horſe that was actually liſted in the Militia, upon any pretence whatever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> 1. Captain <hi>Thomas White</hi> of the old Lord <hi>George Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s Regiment, drew out an hundred Men under the Command of Captain <hi>Johnſton,</hi> who marched with his Party to <hi>Belnamona</hi> in <hi>Kings County,</hi> where he had ſuch good ſucceſs, that by break of day he ſurprized two Troops of Dragoons of Brigadier <hi>Clif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>'s Regiment, and three Troops of Horſe of the Lord <hi>Merrion</hi>'s Regiment, kill'd Lieutenant <hi>Archibald,</hi> Quarter-Maſter <hi>Barnell,</hi> and fifteen Dragoons, took two Enſigns, and other Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, burnt the Town, and returned with a good Booty of Horſes, Arms and Cattel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My</hi> 3. The Governour of <hi>Clonmel,</hi> with a Detachment of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48905:8"/>Horſe, and two Troops of the Militia-Dragoons, marched by Night into the Enemies Quarters toward <hi>Michels-Town;</hi> but not meeting with any of the Rebels, was returning back to his Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, when a Corporal of Horſe making a halt a little behind, was ſhot at by four <hi>Rapparees:</hi> Upon which, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſurroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Wood; and after ſome hours Man-Hunting, killed above thirty of the <hi>Rapparees,</hi> and one <hi>Caſhan</hi> their Captain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> 4. Major <hi>Wood</hi> marched from <hi>Mountmilock</hi> to <hi>Caſtle-Cuff,</hi> with a Party of three hundred Foot, drawn out of Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Lloyd</hi>'s and the Lord <hi>George Hamilton</hi>'s Regiment, and fifty Horſe of Collonel <hi>Byerly</hi>'s. In his march, he divided the Foot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſeveral ſmall Parties, in order to ſurprize the <hi>Rapparees</hi> in the woods and Bogs, keeping with the Horſe along the skirts of the Bog, to hinder their eſcape: By which means, they made a ſhift to kill about ſeventy <hi>Rapparees,</hi> and to take a good num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of their Cattel. Which done, Major <hi>Wood</hi> advanc'd with thirty Foot, and thirty four Horſe, beyond the <hi>Togher</hi> of <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lybone,</hi> and from thence ſent the Cattel homeward under a Guard of thirty Men, and was returning to his Party with thoſe few that were with him, about ten of the Clock in the Morning, when he diſcover'd two Bodies of Men of the late Kings Army, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to conſiſt of four hundred each Body, marching ſilently between the Wood and the Mountains; but who, ſo ſoon as they perceiv'd themſelves to be eſpy'd, beat their Drums; upon which, the Major drew up the chiefeſt part of his whole Party in a Plough'd field, and fac'd 'em: Preſently the Enemies Granadiers came over the Hedge, and made towards the Major, till ſeeing the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſtand firm, they alſo made a halt. Whereupon the Major, apprehending that the thirty Men that guarded the Booty, were not got clear of the Wood, and conſequently might be expoſed to the Enemies Numbers, wheel'd off by the skirt of the Wood to their ſuccor; and by that time he had got his Horſe and Foot over the Bog, he heard the Enemy firing very thick upon the thirty Men, who bravely however oppos'd 'em, under the Command of Lieutenant <hi>Ellis.</hi> The noiſe of this firing brought in fourſcore more of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who had been laid to watch the <hi>Rapparees.</hi> Thereupon Major <hi>Wood</hi> order'd the Foot to march in two Parties on each ſide the River, while he with the Horſe march'd between 'em both. Being in this manner come within ſight of the Enemy, and judging that the Horſe might do moſt ſervice, by fetching a compaſs about, and getting behind
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48905:9"/>the Rebels, he gallop'd round, with an intention to fall upon their Reer; which the Enemy perceiving, and being at the ſame time hard put to it by the Foot, began to make an orderly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat. But then it was, that the Major, unwilling to loſe his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, fell immediately upon-their Flank with his Horſe, and that with ſo much Courage and undaunted Bravery, that he put the Enemy firſt into great diſorder, and ſoon after to an abſolute flight. Both Horſe and Foot purſu'd the Fugitives quite through the Wood down to the Bog, and kill'd about 150 among whom was Capt. <hi>Chales,</hi> with 2 Lieutenants, and took Priſoners Maj. <hi>John Fitz-Patrick</hi> who commanded the whole Force, 5 Captains, 9 Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, 2 Enſigns (belonging to the ſeveral Regiments of Coll. <hi>Butler</hi> of <hi>Ballyraggats,</hi> Collonel <hi>Robert Grace,</hi> Collonel <hi>Charles Moore,</hi> Sir <hi>Morice Euſtace,</hi> and Collonel <hi>Simon Lutterel</hi>'s Dragoons) and a hundred and five private Souldiers, ſix Serjeants, ſeventeen Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals, a Surgcon and three Drums; together with a hundred and fifty Muskets: All which was done by a hundred and ten of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Foot, and thirty four Horſe. With the Foot were Major <hi>Rider,</hi> Captain <hi>Nenny,</hi> Captain <hi>Dixy,</hi> Lieutenant <hi>Barton,</hi> and Enſign <hi>Ruſſel.</hi> With the Horſe were Cornet <hi>Joſhua,</hi> Cornet <hi>Haſlington,</hi> Adjutant <hi>Robinſon,</hi> and Quarter-Maſter <hi>Cadford,</hi> who with their Men, both Horſe and Foot, behaved themſelves with an extraordinary Bravery; gaining ſo conſiderable a Victory over above ſix times their number, with the loſs only of Adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant <hi>Robinſon,</hi> one Corporal, and two Foot-Souldiers kill'd out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and one Trooper wounded.</p>
            <p>The ſame day this memorable Action was performed; a Party of Collonel <hi>Brewer</hi>'s Men were going from <hi>Mullingar</hi> towards <hi>Kinnagan;</hi> at what time a Serjeant and four Souldiers lagging a good way behind, were ſurpriz'd and murther'd by the <hi>Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parees;</hi> only one eſcap'd, whom they left for dead, and whoſe Eyes they had moſt barbarouſly pick'd out with a Skean.</p>
            <p>But the next Day, being the 6th of <hi>May,</hi> three <hi>Rapparees</hi> were taken, who being brought to <hi>Mullingar,</hi> one of them, whoſe Name was <hi>Ellis,</hi> gave Evidence againſt the other two, who were thereupon immediately hanged. The ſame day Captain <hi>Richard Poynts</hi> went out of <hi>Mullingar,</hi> with a hundred Men of that Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, and falling upon a Party of <hi>Rapparees</hi> near <hi>Managhan,</hi> kill'd above forty; and Lieut. Coll. <hi>Hodſon</hi> ſallying out at the ſame time from <hi>Mountmelock,</hi> poſted his Men over night at a Place call'd <hi>Iſikapog;</hi> the morning by break of day, the Foot antred the Woods and Bogs, while the Horſe ſcoured the shirts
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48905:9"/>of both; to the deſtruction of 18 of the <hi>Rapparee</hi> Vermin kill'd out-right, and ſeveral taken Priſoners, among whom was one <hi>O Rourk</hi> their Captain; who becauſe he was notoricuſly known to have committed ſeveral Robberies, was hang'd upon the Place. A fair ſatisfaction, in ſo ſhort a time, for the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the four <hi>Mullingar Engliſh,</hi> and digging out the Eyes of the fifth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> 8. The <hi>French</hi> Convoy arriv'd at <hi>Linner</hi>-Lake, with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, Cloaths and Ammunition, but neither Men nor Mony: The Sieur <hi>de</hi> St. <hi>Ruth,</hi> who is to command the Rebels, and two <hi>French</hi> Lieutenant-Generals, came over in the ſame Ships. And this was lookt upon like the pouring of Brandy down the Throat of a dying Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> 11. A hundred and fifty of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army came to <hi>Caſtle-Lyons,</hi> and took away ſome Cattel from thence: But Coll. <hi>Donep</hi> being there with about 20 <hi>Danes,</hi> and 20 of the Militia-Dragoons, purſu'd the Enemy; at what time a Lieutenant of the <hi>Danes,</hi> with 8 Horſe and 6 Dragoons, getting before the reſt, and overtaking the Rebels at <hi>Ballyderrawne,</hi> beat off 60 from the Hedges which they had lin'd in that part, though with the loſs of the Licutenant, who was there ſlain. But then the Collonel coming up with the reſt of his Party, conſtrain'd the Rebels to run; and being reinforc'd with 50 Men out of the Regiments of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel. <hi>Boyle,</hi> Collonel <hi>St. Leger,</hi> and Captain <hi>Barry</hi>'s Militia-Troops that lay poſted at <hi>Formoy,</hi> they continu'd the purſuit a Mile an half beyond <hi>Kilworth,</hi> kill'd about 50, of which two were Commiſſion-Officers, took 40 Horſes, and ſeveral Silver-hilted Swords, Cloaths, Arms, and other Accoutrements, recover'd the Booty, and got about 30 Cows beſides.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> 14. The Lords Juſtices and Council ſet forth a Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, declaring, That all Popiſh <hi>Iriſh</hi> Inhabirants, where any <hi>Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parees</hi> ſhould commit any Robberies, Burnings or Murthers, or make any Inſurrections, if they did not immediately give notice of ſuch <hi>Rapparees</hi> and Inſurrections, to the Juſtice of Peace or Military Officer next to their Habitations, and aſſiſt them in their taking of ſuch <hi>Rapparees,</hi> and ſuppreſſing ſuch Inſurrections, ſhould be deem'd Confederates with the Rebels, and Enemies to their Majeſties Government, and be proceeded againſt with the utmoſt ſeverity of Military execution. They farther order'd, That no protected <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts ſhould be out of their Houſes after nine at Night, nor ſtir out of their Houſes before four in the Morning,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48905:10"/>upon pain of being put out of their Majeſties Protection. And that after the 30th of <hi>May,</hi> if any Arms or Ammunition ſhould be found in the poſſeſſion of ſuch <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, they ſhould be lookt upon as Rebels, and puniſh'd accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> 26. The Train of Artillery, conſiſting of 36 Pieces of Cannon, and 8 Mortars, ſet forward from <hi>Dublin,</hi> and upon the 30th arriv'd at the general Rendezvouz near <hi>Mullingar.</hi> The ſame day General <hi>Ginkle</hi> went from <hi>Dublin</hi> to the Army, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting General <hi>Douglaſs</hi> to joyn him with 12000 Men from the North.</p>
            <p>They who beheld the vaſt Preparations for this Campaign, had a fair proſpect of their Majeſties extream Care and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for the total Recovery of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and were eaſily convinc'd that the Publick Treaſure was not now as formerly given for the Welfare, but expended for the Deſtruction of the Monarchy; parted with for the Honour of the Nation, but waſted upon Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, while they beheld all the proper Ports of the Kingdom con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually fill'd with Ships and Veſſels, ſome tranſporting Money, others Recruits to the Army; while they beheld ſuch amazing Quantities of Proviſion, Arms and Ammunition; 500 Draught-Horſes at a time for the Carriages, and ſuch other vaſt ſtores for the Artillery, with all other Neceſſaries for ſo great an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize. Which ſhews the difference of a Nation's being under the Care of good Stewards, and from being under the negligent Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government of Profuſeneſs and unthrifty Prodigality.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> they were as buſie at the ſame time, as their Aſſiſtance would permit 'em: And certain information was given, That their new <hi>French</hi> General <hi>St. Ruth,</hi> iſſu'd out all his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the <hi>French</hi> King's Name, and requir'd ſeveral of the Rebel's Officers to take new Commiſſions under the <hi>French</hi> King, in proſecution of a Deſign of ſubjecting <hi>Ireland</hi> to <hi>France,</hi> that had been long carried on in that Kingdom by <hi>Abbot Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velle,</hi> and of which his own Letters to a great Perſon in <hi>France,</hi> that have been ſince intercepted, are a ſufficient Evidence.</p>
            <p>But before we launch into the grand Campaign, there is this Obſervation to be made, That though theſe leſſer Encounters which have been hitherto related, may ſeem to be of little value, yet conſidering the continu'd ſucceſs of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> though for the moſt part their Parties were much inferior to the Enemy, and the continu'd bad Fortune of the Rebels, ſuch a Proſperity muſt needs be a great Encouragement to the one ſide, and no
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48905:10"/>ſmall Diſheartning to the other, not to have one ſmile of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in their Favor. Add to this, the picking up of ſo many of the Enemy for Hawks-meat, not ſuddenly taken notice of by a curſory Reading, was like a kind of Hectick Feaver, waſting their Body by degrees; which if the condition of the Kingdom would have endur'd it, muſt have conſum'd the whole Bulk of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at the long run. For moſt certainly it may be found by an eaſie computation, that in leſs than two Months before the Campaign open'd, the Rebels loſt, by theſe petty Gleanings, 1079, Men kill'd out right, and above 230 Priſoners, in all 1309 Men, of which ſome were conſiderable Officers, and perhaps in the Number of the moſt experienc'd and daring Commanders; whereas about 40 was the utmoſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> loſs; beſides, that the ill <hi>Omen</hi> of being always beaten, makes a deep impreſſion in the Minds of Men more couragious than the <hi>Iriſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now all things being in a readineſs for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to take the Field, General <hi>Ginkle,</hi> Commander in Chief of their Ma je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Forces in the Kingdom in <hi>Ireland,</hi> upon the 6th of <hi>May,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp'd from <hi>Mullingar;</hi> and being joyn'd the ſame day by Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Douglaſs</hi> with the Northern Forces, which made up the whole Army 15 Battalions of Foot, and 3000 Horſe, upon the 7th of <hi>May</hi> came before <hi>Ballymore,</hi> ſeated upon a tongue of firm Land, jetting out into a Lake, being in circumference about a Mile, ending on the two ſides with Bogs that are unacceſſible, which leave but a very ſtreight Avenue from the main Land. The Enemy had fortified this place with two Retrenchments in the Winter, of which the firſt was a Horn-work, the ſecond two whole Baſtions, whoſe outward Curtains on each ſide extended down to the Lake; and within the laſt Retrenchment was an old <hi>Daniſh</hi> Mount, ſo fortified as that it made a third Retreat.</p>
            <p>Upon the General's approach to the Town, the Marquiſs <hi>de Rovigny</hi> was ſent before with a ſtrong Detachment of Horſe and Dragoons, to poſſeſs himſelf of a Paſs between the Town and <hi>Athlone;</hi> and as ſoon as the advanc'd part of the Army appear'd upon the Hills that look into the Fort, the Enemy began to play upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> with two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ield-Pieces, but without doing any harm. In the mean time a Detachment of Foot was ſent to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs themſelves of the Rebels out Poſts, which they quitted upon the approach of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ran as faſt as they could into <hi>Ballymore;</hi> only a Serjeant and twelve Men continu'd firing out of a round Tower, and kill'd two of the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> But the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48905:11"/>Tower ſoon after being taken by Aſſault, the Serjeant was hang'd upon a high Hill, in ſight of the Enemy, for firing upon the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers after the Communication was cut off from him and the Town. That Night the Beſiegers raiſed five different Batteries; the firſt of 12 Pounders, the ſecond of ſix 18 Pounders, to ruin the ſecond Retrenchment; the third of 8 Field-Pieces to break the Palliſadoes; the fourth of four 18 Pounders, and two 12 Pounders, which batter'd the Horn-work; as alſo a Lodgment on the ſame ſide for three Mortar pieces. All which were brought to play the ſame Night. About eight of the Clock the next Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the General ſent a Meſſage to the Governour, <hi>That if he and the Garriſon would ſurrender within two Hours, he would ſave their Lives, and receive 'em as Priſoners of War: If not, that they ſhould expect no quarter.</hi> To which the Governor returning a ſhuffling fort of an Anſwer, in hopes to get better Terms, the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries play'd on, and about Noon the Breaches of the firſt and ſecond Retrenchments were ſo far advanc'd, and the Palliſado's ſo effectually cut down, that the General reſolv'd to ſtorm the Town in five ſeveral Places, on the Hornwork, and the two ſides of the Bog by help of Faggots, and by that means to divide the Garriſon, which conſiſted of 1000 Men. The Beſiegers alſo had four large Wherries a float upon the Lake, which were brought from <hi>Dublin</hi> with a great deal of trouble, into which were put an hundred and fifty Granadiers, that at the time of the general Aſlault, were to attack the Beſieg'd on that ſide that lay open to the Lake. All which Preparations, and their own Condition, put them into ſo great a Conſternation, that they hung out ſeveral white Flags; and about ſeven a Clock in the Evening, when they left off firing on both ſides, the Governour Collonel <hi>Mich. Bourk,</hi> and ſeveral Officers came out, and ſubmitted to the General's Mercy.</p>
            <p>Upon the 9th of <hi>May</hi> the Garriſon came forth, conſiſting of 780 Men, drawn out of the Enemies ſtanding-Army, beſides 4 Field-Officers, 16 Captains, 14 Lieutenants, 12 Enſigns and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and 259 <hi>Rapparees,</hi> all well arm'd; who all laying down their Arms, were made Priſoners in the innermoſt part of the Fort. Beſides the Garriſon, there were above 600 Women and Children, among whom a Load of Ammunition-Bread was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to be diſtributed. There was found in the Place ſeveral Sacks of <hi>French</hi> Oat-meal, about ten Barrels of Powder, with Shot proportionable in their Magazine, two Field pieces and about
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48905:11"/>three hundred Head of Cattel, and five hundred Sheep, which were given to the Souldiers.</p>
            <p>The ſame Night that the Town ſurrendred, there was a hot Alarum that the Enemy was at hand, with a Body of 25000 Men; which occaſion'd the Beſiegers to double their Guards, and ſend out a ſtrong Party of Horſe and Foot toward <hi>Athlone,</hi> who within two Miles of that place, ſurpriz'd an advanc'd Guard of the Enemies aſleep the main Body conſiſting of 1000 Men who retreated in ſafety, in regard the <hi>engliſh</hi> had no Orders to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance any farther.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as the Town was taken, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> fell to work in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing the Breaches, making ſome additions of new Works, and levelling the Batteries; and a Garriſon was put into it of 500 Men: The Priſoners, being 51 Officers, and 900 Souldiers, were ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to <hi>Mullingar,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Dublin.</hi> After this, the General lay a while encamp'd near <hi>Ballymore,</hi> in expectation of the Prince of <hi>Wirtemberg,</hi> who upon the 4th of <hi>June</hi> decamp'd from <hi>Thurles,</hi> with the Forces under his Command, conſiſting of 12000 Horſe and Foot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> 5. They came to <hi>Roſcreagh,</hi> where they reſted all the next day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> 7. They marched on to <hi>Bir;</hi> and upon <hi>June</hi> the 10th, continu'd their march, and came to <hi>Streanes</hi> Town the 14th, and upon the 18th joyn'd the General, ſix Miles farther in the way to <hi>Athlone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the 18 of <hi>June,</hi> early in the Morning, the Army march'd from <hi>Ballymore;</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Wirtemberg</hi> having joyn'd the General, they encampt at <hi>Ballymore</hi>'s Paſs; from whence a ſtrong Detachment of Horſe and Dragoons was fent to <hi>Ath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the 19th the Army came before the Place, paſſing through many narrow Lanes, which might have coſt a great many Men, had the Enemy as floutly defended 'em, as they might have done; and it ſeem'd a new ſight, to behold none but <hi>French</hi> Colours in four parts of an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Garriſon.</p>
            <p>Upon the 20th of <hi>June,</hi> a Battery of ten 18 Pounders was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd, and began to play upon the Baſtion near the Water ſide looking toward <hi>Lanesborough;</hi> and the Guns were ſo well directed, that by three of the Clock in the Afternoon, the whole Face, Flank, and part of the Curtain, was laid in Ruins; and thereupon the General gave Orders for an Aſſault to be made, which was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48905:12"/>in this manner: Firſt march'd 300 detach'd Granadiers, then 50 Pioneers with Bavins, next 200 Fuziliers, and then 2 Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of Foot, commanded by Brigadier <hi>Stewart;</hi> after which follow'd 200 Pioneers with more Bavins, and 20 Men with Felling-Axes, to cut away any Barricado of the Enemies they might meet in their way. All things being thus in a readineſs, about ſix in the Evening the Sign was given, by a diſcharge of all the Cannon in Battery: Upon which, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> advanc'd in very good Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Aſſault. The Enemy ſeem'd reſolv'd at firſt to have maintain'd the Breach; but upon the firſt ſight of the Hand-Granadiers, they fled, retiring in great conſuſion to <hi>Connaught</hi>-ſide, divers alſo leaping over the <hi>Shannon</hi> for haſte: So that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had nothing to do but to enter; which the whole Party did, and advanc'd to the Bridge; where lying open to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhot from the other ſide, ſeveral of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were kill'd and wounded, till the Enginiers had compleated ſome Blinds to cover them from the Town. In this Action however, not above 20 of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were wounded, and ſome few ſlain out-right: In the number of the firſt was Brigadier <hi>Stewart,</hi> who was ſhot in the right Arm and in the Neck, but not dangerouſly; but Lieut. Coll. <hi>Gore,</hi> that led on the Granadiers, was ſhot at the Breach; and Lieutenant <hi>Kirk</hi> of <hi>Villiars</hi>'s Regiment, was unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately kill'd by a Cannon-Ball, as he was viewing the Place from the top of a Hill that was juſt by.</p>
            <p>On the 24th, a private Souldier ſeeing one of the Enemies Colours floating upon the River near the Bridge, threw himſelf into the Water; and though many ſhot were made at him, brought it off, and preſented it to the General, who gave him a good Reward.</p>
            <p>And thus one part of the Town being taken, upon the 25th of <hi>June,</hi> the Batteries againſt the other part of it were all finiſh'd, and thirty two Pieces of Cannon, and ſix Mortars, planted upon 'em, which play'd upon the Caſtle and the Enemies Works, on the other ſide of the River, with great ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>The 27th at Night the Souldiers wrought hard to repair the Stone-Bridge, of which two Arches were broken down by the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: One of them was quite made up, and the other almoſt fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, when early next Morning the Enemy pull'd away ſome of the Planks, and threw them into the River; which made the <hi>Engliſh</hi> reſolve to carry on a cloſe Gallery upon the Bridge; which being done accordingly, Orders were given for ſtorming
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48905:12"/>the Place on the 29th, at ſeven in the Morning; but before all things were in a readineſs for it, a ſmall Party of the Enemy came out, and ſet fire to the Gallery, though with the loſs of moſt of their Lives. This Accident occaſion'd the deferring the Aſſault till the next day. In the mean time the Cannon and Bombs continually play'd upon the Town and Caſtle, doing moſt terrible execution. However, the ſucceſs the Enemy had in burning the Gallery, gave them ſo great aſſurance, that they did not expect to be ſo ſoon attackt.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, all things being in a readineſs, in purſuance of the Orders given by General <hi>Ginkle,</hi> upon <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 30th of <hi>June,</hi> about four a Clock in the Afternoon, the Attack was made by 1500 Granadiers, and 6 Battalions of Foot ſtanding ready to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port 'em, if occaſion ſhould be. The Signal was the ringing of the <hi>Church bell,</hi> upon which the Granadiers (with whom M.G. <hi>Talmaſh,</hi> tho' he did not Command that day, went along as a Voluntier) entred the Ford, which was the only Paſſage the Aſſailants had, in regard the Bridge was ſo broken, that they could not get over it. The Enemy at firſt fired very ſmartly, but the Aſſailants, who waded up to their Breaſts in Water with continual <hi>Huzzaing,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd under the ſhelter of their own Cannon; and throwing their Granadoes, forc'd the Enemy from their Poſts and Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; and in leſs than half an hours time, made themſelves en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely Maſters of the Town, with all their Enemies Works and the Ruins of the Caſtle. Major-General <hi>Maxwel,</hi> with ſeveral other Officers, and 200 common Souldiers, were taken Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and between 1000 and 1200 were kill'd upon the Place, beſides Officers of note, ſuch as were Brigadier <hi>Mackelicuddy,</hi> Collonels <hi>Mac-Mahoon, O Neale, O Gara,</hi> Lieut Collonels <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genis</hi> and <hi>Barnwel;</hi> and Maj. <hi>Murray,</hi> Coll. <hi>Grace,</hi> being ſlain the day before: The reſt eſcap'd over the Ramparts, and fled to the Enemies Camp; from whence ſome Battalions were coming to their Relief; but meeting with the Fugitives, and receiving a warm Salute from thoſe very Works that were ſo very lately their own, they retreated back to their Camp.</p>
            <p>Of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were about 20 ſlain, and 30 wounded; while all, both Officers and Souldiers, behav'd themſelves beyond an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Imagination, and perhaps beyond the Parallel of many Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, where ſo much Bravery of Enterprize is rarely to be found, for only 3000 Men to aſſail a fortified Town, croſs a River, and make themſelves Maſters of it in ſo ſhort a time, in the very
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48905:13"/>face and view of the Enemy; an Action, with which only the Taking of <hi>Buda</hi> can ſtand in competition: Particularly the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor-Generals <hi>Teteau</hi> and <hi>Mackay,</hi> Brigadier <hi>de la Meloniere,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Heſſe-Dermſtadt,</hi> who conducted the Attack; the Prince of <hi>Wirtemberg,</hi> Major-General <hi>Talmaſh,</hi> Count <hi>Naſſau,</hi> and Brigadier <hi>Bellaſis,</hi> merited laſting Honour, in contributing ſo greatly as they did, by their Conduct and Courage, to the good ſucceſs of ſo ſignal an Atchievment. There were in the Town ſix Pieces of Braſs Cannon, and two Mortars; but the ſtores of Powder, Bullet and Proviſions, were but ſmall. The Town and Caſtle were reduc'd to a heap of Ruins; and the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners ſaid, That before the Attack, there were kill'd in the Town about 1200 Men, by the Beſiegers Cannon and Bombs, of which, nor of their Bullets or Stones, the Aſſailants were no Niggards, as having beſtow'd upon the Place, before it was taken, 10000 Bullets, 600 Bombs, and ſeveral Tun of Stones.</p>
            <p>The Town being thus reduc'd, the Enemy decamp'd in the Night-time, between the 30th of <hi>June,</hi> and 1ſt of <hi>July,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated ten Miles off, to a Place call'd <hi>Bally-Naſh,</hi> where they lay with the River <hi>Soke</hi> before 'em, giving out that they deſign'd to ſtand a Battel: In purſuance of which Reſolution, they at the ſame time quitted <hi>Slego, James</hi>-Town, and <hi>Lanesborough,</hi> in ſo much haſte, that they left their Powder and great Guns behind 'em.</p>
            <p>On the 10th of <hi>July</hi> General <hi>Ginkle</hi> paſs'd the <hi>Shannon</hi> at <hi>Ath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone;</hi> the Foot over a Bridge of Boats below the Town, the Horſe and Artillery over the Stone-Bridge; and that Night they encamp'd about five Miles from <hi>Athlone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 11th they march'd, and encampt on the left ſide of <hi>Ballinaſlow,</hi> upon the River <hi>Suc,</hi> with in three Miles of the Enemy, who lay very advantagiouſly encampt at <hi>Aghriam,</hi> their left Wing ſtretching out toward <hi>Kilkon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el</hi> Abby, and their right upon <hi>Rilcommodon</hi>-Hills: Before them lay two Bogs, between which, the Road leads to <hi>Galloway.</hi> On their left lay the Ruins of an old Caſtle, which was entrench'd and lin'd with Foot; and on their right they had made ſeveral Entrenchments for the ſecurity of their Camp.</p>
            <p>On the 14th, in the Morning, the Army march'd from <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linaſlow,</hi> and by eleven a Clock had paſs'd the River <hi>Suc,</hi> the Horſe at two Fords, and the Foot over the Stone-Bridge: Where after ſome skirmiſhing, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> drove in the Enemies out-Guards,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48905:13"/>and the left Wing of their Majeſties Army drew beyond the Bog, which cover'd the Enemies right Wing, and made room for the Foot to advance between that and them. In the mean time, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cannon had diſlodg'd the Rebels Horſe, from the end of the narrow Lane that leads to <hi>Aghriam,</hi> and the Kings Horſe and Foot took up their Poſt there, ſtill pouring over Men into a ſmall ſpot of firm Land, that lay between the two Bogs and the old Caſtle.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the Enemy drew down great Bodies of Horſe and Foot upon the left Wing of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and were ſo ſtrongly poſted behind the high Banks that lay one behind a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, that the Foot had a very warm diſpute with the Rebels for two hours, but at laſt forc'd 'em to give ground, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding new Supplies both of Horſe and Foot were ſtill ſent by the Rebels to relieve and ſecond thoſe that gave way. At the ſame time alſo three Battalions of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Foot advanc'd on the right hand, over the skirt of the Bog, and a little River that ſupplies the <hi>Suc,</hi> into a Corn-Field, where they were warmly entertain'd by ſeveral of the Enemies Battalions and Squadrons. However, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> maintain'd their ground till more Regiments came to their aſſiſtance; and forcing the-Enemy to retreat, gave time for the right Wing of Horſe to come on, who immediately charg'd up the Hills upon the Squadrons of the Enemy; at what time the left Wing of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> having beaten the <hi>Iriſh</hi> from their ground, and the Right preſſing hard upon 'em at the ſame time, put 'em into an abſolute Rout.</p>
            <p>The Victors purſu'd the flying Rebels about four Miles; for Night would not permit 'em to do it any farther, in regard it was ſix a Clock in the Afternoon before both Armies engag'd, and eight in the Evening before the Enemy was abſolutely routed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Iriſh</hi> were never known to fight with more Reſolution, eſpecially the Foot; beſides, that the Rebels were much ſuperior to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in number, being no leſs than 20000 Foot, and 8000 Horſe and Dragoons, with all the Advantage moreover imaginable, that the Situation of the Ground could afford 'em However, the ſuperiour Valour and Conduct of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> was ſuch, as ſurmounted all thoſe Diſadvantages, and wreſted a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Victory out of the hands of an Enemy more ſtubborn than had been known for ſome Ages in that Kingdom. But it was the laſt Effort, <hi>pro Aris &amp; Focis,</hi> wherein the gaſping Honour of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48905:14"/>Choice of all the Catholick Nobility and Gentry of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſtrugled to do its utmoſt.</p>
            <p>Of the Enemy 5000, or if you will believe Major-General <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington,</hi> who was one of the Priſoners, 8000 were ſlain upon the Place; among whom was the <hi>French</hi> General <hi>St. Ruth,</hi> who was ſlain by a Cannon Bullet; the Lord <hi>Galloway,</hi> Coll. <hi>Barker,</hi> Coll. <hi>Moore,</hi> and Coll. <hi>Baggot,</hi> with ſeveral others.</p>
            <p>The Priſoners of note were Maj. Gen. <hi>Hamilton,</hi> Brigadier <hi>Tate,</hi> Lord <hi>Bellew,</hi> Brigadier <hi>Gourdon O Neale,</hi> Lieut. Coll. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> wounded.</p>
            <p>Maj. Gen. <hi>Dorrington,</hi> Lord <hi>Slane,</hi> Lord <hi>Kilmore,</hi> Lord <hi>Ruffin,</hi> Coll. <hi>Butler,</hi> Coll. <hi>Grace,</hi> Maj. <hi>Lawleſs,</hi> Coll. <hi>Walter Bourk,</hi> Lieut. Coll. <hi>John Baggot,</hi> Lieut. Coll. <hi>James Braudier,</hi> Maj. <hi>William. Bourk.</hi> Maj. <hi>Edmund Butler,</hi> 9 Captains, 11 Lieutenants, 7 En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, 2 Corporals, 8 Quarter-Maſters, 2 Serjeants, 190 private Souldiers, in the hands of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Provoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Priſoners in the <hi>Dutch</hi> Provoſt's Cuſtody.</label> Major <hi>Ter. Kelly,</hi> 18 Captains 20 Lieutenants, 4 Cornets, 4 Quarter Maſters, 13 Enſigns, 1 Adjutant, and 217 private Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: In all 407, which were afterwards made up full 500.</p>
            <p>Trophies of Honour were alſo taken, 12 Standards, 30 Colours, and one Kettle-Drum; with which the Lord <hi>O Bryan</hi> was ſent into <hi>England,</hi> to preſent 'em to the Queen.</p>
            <p>Add to this, That never better Conduct nor Gallantry was ever ſhewn, than among the General Officers; never more Bravery and Reſolution ſeen among private Souldiers, who, with a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing Courage and undaunted Fury, preſt on, beat down all before 'em, and forc'd the Enemy from their advantagious Poſts and Entrenchments, to make way for Victory and a glorious Triumph, with the loſs of no more than 500 ſlain, and 700 wounded. Of the number of the ſlain were Maj. Gen. <hi>Holtſtaple,</hi> Coll. <hi>Charles Herbert,</hi> firſt taken Priſoner at the beginning of the Fight, and afterwards inhumanly murther'd by the Rebels when they ſaw the Battel loſt; Coll. <hi>Mongatz</hi> of the <hi>Danes,</hi> Maj. <hi>Petit</hi> of <hi>Bel-Caſtle</hi>'s Regiment, Maj. <hi>Deveniſh</hi> of <hi>Earle</hi>'s, Maj. <hi>Colt</hi> of <hi>Brewer</hi>'s, Maj. <hi>Cornwal</hi> and Maj. <hi>Fox,</hi> of <hi>Fouke</hi>'s, with divers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeriour Officers. Among the wounded were the Prince of <hi>Heſſe-Dermstadt,</hi> the Lord <hi>George Hamilton,</hi> the Lord <hi>Cutts,</hi> Coll. <hi>Earle,</hi> Lieut. Coll. <hi>Brudenell,</hi> with ſome others.</p>
            <p>After the Battel was over, the General encampt where the <hi>wiſh</hi> lay, and the next day, being the 13th of <hi>June,</hi> ſent away
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48905:14"/>Brigadier <hi>Eppinger</hi> with a Detachment of 1200 Horſe Horſe and Dragoons, to ſeize <hi>Portumney,</hi> where the Rebels had a great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazine of Proviſions, who ſoon poſſeſs'd himſelf of it; and the next day, being the 14th, the Fort and Caſtie of <hi>Banaker</hi> ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to Major <hi>Wood;</hi> whereby the <hi>Engliſh</hi> became Maſters of all the Paſſes upon the <hi>Shannon,</hi> except <hi>Limerick,</hi> and thoſe within eight Miles of it.</p>
            <p>Upon the 17th of <hi>July</hi> the Army advanc'd to <hi>Loghreah,</hi> and from thence upon the 19th to <hi>Athenree,</hi> where the General left about 3000 Horſe, under the Command of Lieutenant-General <hi>Scravenmore,</hi> and Major-General <hi>Rovigny,</hi> to obſerve the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies motion, but more eſpecially to ſecure the free Paſſage of the Convoys and great Guns; and from thence advanc'd to <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loway.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So ſoon as the General came before the Place, he ſent a Trumpet to the Lord <hi>Dillon,</hi> Governour of the Town, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd him the Benefit of the Lords Juſtices Proclamation of the 7th of <hi>July,</hi> in caſe he ſurrondred before the Cannon were brought to fire upon the Garriſon. His Anſwer was, <hi>That Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur</hi> d'Uſſone, <hi>who Commanded, was of the ſame Opinion with him and the reſt of the Officers, and that they reſolv'd to defend the Place to the last.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> immediately made their Approaches, and the next day, being the 20th, by break of day, the Beſiegers attack'd a Fort upon a Hill, which commanded a Valley between the Town and them. The Granadiers that were drawn out for this Action, march'd with that ſilence, that they got to the ſoot of the <hi>Glacis,</hi> before they were diſcover'd by the Enemy; at what time delivering their Granadoes, they went on directly to the Palliſadoes, and entred the Fort without oppoſition, and made themſelves Maſters of it without the loſs of one Man, the Enemy crying out for Quarter, which was readily granted.</p>
            <p>Immediately the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> having thus taken the Fort, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench'd themſelves in the Valley; at what time the General hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that <hi>Baldarick O Donnel</hi> was on his march, in order to throw himſelf and and his Brigade into the Place, the Tin-Boats were immediately launch'd in the River, and ſix Regiments of Foot and four of Horſe ſent over the River, and poſted full in the way where <hi>Baldarick</hi> was to paſs: Who finding it impoſſible for him to bring about his Deſign, retreated with his Rabble into the Country of <hi>Mayo,</hi> burning and deſtroying all before him.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48905:15"/>The taking this Fort, and croſſing over the River ſo ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, may well be thought to have frighted the Enemy into a Treaty; for upon the 21ſt, about ten in the Morning, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour ſent for a ſafe Conduct for ſome Perſons he intended to ſend to the General, in order to a Capitulation: Which being granted, three Lieurenant Collonels came forth as Hoſtages, in the Afternoon. The Treaty laſted the reſt of the day and night, at what time the Commiſſioners were ublig'd to go back, and conſult their Superior Officers. But at laſt it was agreed,</p>
            <p>That the next <hi>Sunday,</hi> being the 26 of <hi>July,</hi> in the Morning, the Town ſhould be deliver'd to ſuch Officers as the General ſhould appoint; and that in the mean time five Hoſtages ſhould be deliver'd to the Beſiegers, for due performance of Articles; and that all the Out-works of the Town ſhould be put into their hands.</p>
            <p>That the Enemy ſhould forbear to fortifie in the mean time, and withdraw all their Cannon from the Walls; but that the Beſiegers ſhould be permitted to work and poſt themſelves where they would, provided they came not within three yards of the Wall, nor planted any Cannon upon the Battery they made.</p>
            <p>That the Garriſon and Townſmen that remain'd behind, ſhould have the Benefit of the Lords Juſtices Proclamation, which gives them their Eſtates and Liberties.</p>
            <p>That they who had a mind to depart, ſhould be conducted ſafe to <hi>Limerick,</hi> with their Arms, Drums beating, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with ſix Pieces of Cannon.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, That they ſhall have the liberty to ſend to the Lord <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> to acquaint him with what they had done, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him to do the ſame at <hi>Limerick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to this Capitulation, they ſent the Lord <hi>Clanriccard,</hi> and four Officers more, for Hoſtages, and allow'd two Perſons appointed by the General, to enter into the Place, and take an account of the Stores, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus upon the 26th of <hi>July</hi> was the City of <hi>Galloway</hi> actually ſurrendred, the Garriſon marching out in the Morning, and <hi>a'<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſſone,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Lieutenant-General, departing the Town two or three hours before the reſt, as it were <hi>Incognito;</hi> being a Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity deſired by the Monſieur, and with no leſs Generoſity allow'd by General <hi>Ginkle;</hi> who as ſoon as the Town was clear of the Rebels, put into it three Regiments of Foot, under the Command <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Sir <hi>Henry Bellaſis.</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:48905:15"/>
               <hi>Galloway</hi> being thus reduc'd, upon the 28th of <hi>July,</hi> the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Army ſet forward from thence toward <hi>Portumney,</hi> where the great Cannon for Battery was to meet them from <hi>Athlone:</hi> And there it was that the General receiv'd advice, That Captain <hi>Coale,</hi> with a Squadron of <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Men of War, and the Proviſion and Ammunition-Ships from <hi>Kinſale,</hi> was arriv'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Galloway;</hi> upon which, the General order'd him imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to ſail away for the <hi>Shannon.</hi> From <hi>Athernee,</hi> the Army advanc'd to <hi>Banabar</hi>-Bridge, where they were joyn'd by ſeven Regiments more that lay Quarter'd in thoſe parts; and while the General ſtay'd there, a great number of Draught-Horſes were taken up, in order to carty Proviſion and Ammunition to the Camp. At the ſame time alſo, ſeveral Deſerters came from the Enemy; who gave an account, That the <hi>French</hi> that were in <hi>Limerick,</hi> had been endeavouring to get off a Night or two be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; but perceiving ſeveral <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships in the mouth of the River, they return'd back again. They further inform'd, that there were above twenty Merchant Ships and two Privateers, all laden and bound for <hi>France.</hi> Whereupon Orders were ſent to Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Coale,</hi> who commanded the Squadron then lying in the <hi>Shan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> to take care to ſecure thoſe Veſſels, and prevent their get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out.</p>
            <p>Upon the 3d of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> decampt from <hi>Banabar,</hi> and the ſame day Brigadier <hi>Leveſon,</hi> with 500 Horſe and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, got before, and in the Evening came to <hi>Nenagh;</hi> upon whoſe approach, the Governour, Brigadier <hi>Carroll</hi> quitted the Place in great haſte, having firſt ſet it on fire; which, however, it was ſoon put out, by eleven of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who hapned to be Priſoners there, and were left behind.</p>
            <p>On the 6th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> Collon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l <hi>Mitchelhourn</hi> having block'd up <hi>Slego</hi> on both ſides, the Governour Sir <hi>Teague O Regan,</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to a Capitulation, and ſign'd Articles the ſame day, to ſurrender the Town by the 15th next enſuing. But afterwards, out of that ſame treacherous Inconſtancy, natural to the meer <hi>Iriſh,</hi> he refuſed to yield upon the Capitulations he had ſign'd. So that a more numerous Force was drawn out, and ſent away to joyn with 3000 of the <hi>Militia,</hi> to bring him to another ſort of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time alſo <hi>Baldaric O Donnel,</hi> ſormerly a Collonel in <hi>Spain,</hi> and ſaid to be the true Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> whoſe Name has hitherto made a great Noiſe among the ſuperſtitious <hi>Iriſh,</hi> that pin their Faith upon Prophecies, ſent to the General a Propoſal
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48905:16"/>of ſome Conditions which he deſired might be granted to him and his Followers, upon their laying down their Arms; and that for the preſent, an Article for a Ceſſation might be allow'd him, for continuing unmoleſted with his Men, in ſome place to be aſſign'd him, till their Majeſties Pleaſure ſhould be known con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Demands.</p>
            <p>Upon the 7th or 8th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the <hi>Militia</hi> of the County of <hi>Cork</hi> made an Incurſion into the Rebels Quarters, beyond <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> under the Command of Collonel <hi>Beecher,</hi> and Lieutenant-Collonel <hi>Moore;</hi> who in their march to joyn with Lieutenant-Collonel <hi>Freek,</hi> Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Roberts,</hi> Major <hi>Wade,</hi> and Major <hi>Morris,</hi> met with a Body of the Enemy, conſiſting of 400 Men, near <hi>Skibberteine,</hi> which they preſently defeated, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling above 60, and taking ſeveral Priſoners. Which done, they joyn'd the reſt of the Party; and making up 500 in all, march'd toward a place where they were inform'd that <hi>Mac-Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Moore,</hi> and <hi>O Danavan,</hi> lay with their Regiments; and with great difficulty got over a Paſs, which the Rebels might have defended with 20 Men, againſt 2000. Which put the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my into ſuch a Conſternation, that they betook themſelves to their Heels, in ſo great a confuſion, that they left behind, for a Prey to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> a thouſand Head of Black Cattle, five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Garrans, as many Goats, two thouſand Sheep, and ſtore of other Booty.</p>
            <p>Much about the ſame time, a Veſſel, on board of which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>St. Ruth</hi>'s Goods and Plunder, attempting to get out of the <hi>Shan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> was taken by one of their Majeſties Frigats that was cruiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about the Mouth of the River; at what time two other Ships, in which were <hi>Sarsfield</hi>'s Lady, and ſome other Perſons of Quality, obſerving, as good luck for them would have it, the Misfortune of the firſt Veſſel, return'd back to <hi>Limerick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the 11th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the General march'd from <hi>Nenagh</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <hi>Shadey,</hi> about two Miles from the Silver Mines. The next day he advanc'd to <hi>Tullen,</hi> and upon the 14th, to <hi>Caricken-Lyſh,</hi> which is about four Miles from <hi>Limerick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the 15th, the General went with 1500 Horſe and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, within ſight of the Town; and having beaten in the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies out Guards, took a view of the Rebels Works, from the Hills where their Majeſties Artillery was lodg'd the laſt Year.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:48905:16"/>
            <p>On the 16th, being <hi>Sunday,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> who depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this Life the <hi>Friday</hi> before, as it was certainly ſaid, out of meer Anguiſh of Mind, to ſee the ruinous Condition of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's Affairs, was buried at <hi>Limerick;</hi> who being thus laid in his Grave, a Commiſſion was produc'd from the late King, which Mr. <hi>Plowden,</hi> formerly one of the Commiſſioners of the Revenue in <hi>Ireland,</hi> had brought but a little before from <hi>France,</hi> appoine ting Sir <hi>Alexander Fitton,</hi> Sir <hi>Richard Neagle,</hi> and the ſaid Mr. <hi>Plowden,</hi> Juſtices of <hi>Ireland;</hi> who immediately, by virtue of the ſame Commiſſion, took upon 'em to act, within the narrow Confines of <hi>Limerick,</hi> as Lords Juſtices of that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time Collonel <hi>Henry Lutterell</hi> had been ſeiz'd by order of the <hi>French</hi> Lieut. gen. <hi>d'<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſſone,</hi> for having made ſome Propoſals for a Surrender; and was ſentenc'd, by a Court-Martial, to be ſhot to Death. Of which General <hi>Ginckle</hi> being inform'd, ſent word to the <hi>French</hi> Monſieur by a Trumpet, That if any Man were put to death for having a Mind to come over to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> he would revenge it double upon the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Priſoners.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſt</hi> 25. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army drew near <hi>Limerick,</hi> and drove the Enemy from all their ſeveral Forts and Places of defence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Town; of which they quitted ſome upon the approach of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Nevertheleſs, in another Fort which they had new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly built, and wherein they had ſix hundred Men, they made a ſhew of greater Reſiſtance; but upon the advance of fourſcore Granadiers to attack it, they only gave one general diſcharge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 'em, and then made a running Retreat by a Covert-way, within their Flank Lines, which they had newly raiſed round about the Town.</p>
            <p>The next Morning, a conſiderable Detachment of Horſe and Foot was ſent away, with ſome Cannon, under the Command of the Prince of <hi>Heſſe-Dermſtadt,</hi> to take in <hi>Caſtle-Connel,</hi> where the Enemy had a ſtrong Garriſon: And another Party was ſent to reduce three other Caſtles, in the Enemies poſſeſſion, that lay upon the River below the Town.</p>
            <p>Upon the 25th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the whole Army decamping from <hi>Carrick-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gliſh,</hi> about three in the Afternoon came before <hi>Lime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> the left Wing reaching to the River; but in regard the Enemy had planted two Pieces of Cannon on the other ſide of the River, to the Diſadvantage of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> a Regiment of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, and another of Horſe, that were poſted: neareſt to the Banks of the Stream, were conſtrain'd to remove to a little far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48905:17"/>diſtance out of Harm's way. Being thus come before the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Town, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> advanc'd to <hi>Cromwel</hi> Fort, without any oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, the Enemy quitting both that and the Line of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, which they had made to the Church, and retreating to their Intrenchments that were nearer the Town. And at the ſame time, a Derachment of fourſcore Granadiers were imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately order'd to attack one of their Out-works, which was a new Fort, and guarded by ſix hundred Men; which upon the advancing of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> they abandon'd after one ſingle diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, and fled by the Covert-way into the Town. Upon which, the Granadiers entred the Fort; and purſuing the Fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, kill'd ſeveral, and took about twenty Priſoners, with the loſs of no more than one Man. Only one unhappy Accident ſell out that night, that Collonel <hi>Donep</hi> of the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Horſe, was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately ſlain by a Random-ſhot.</p>
            <p>The 26th the heavy Cannon and Mortars arriv'd, and the Souldiers began to work upon the Lines of Communication.</p>
            <p>The 27th a Battery was raiſed by the Beſiegers againſt <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> Bridge; and the ſame day Lieutenant-General <hi>Scraven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> was ſent with a Detachment to reduce <hi>Caſtle O Gunnel,</hi> which preſently ſurrendred at diſcretion; ſo that the whole Garriſon, conſiſting of a hundred and fifty Men, were all made Priſoners of War. At the ſame time ſome lighter <hi>Engliſh</hi> Frigats made up, and caſt Anchor within ſight of the Town, while Captain <hi>Cole</hi> with the reſt of the Squadron lay about ſix Miles off. 'Tis ſaid that the Beſieged, upon the firſt appearance of the ſmall Frigats, expreſſed an extraordinary Joy, believing them to have been <hi>French;</hi> but were as much appall'd, when they found their unlucky Miſtake.</p>
            <p>The 28th <hi>Castle-Connel</hi> ſurrendred to the Prince of <hi>Heſſe-Derm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtadt,</hi> which was attended with the ſurrender of ſeveral other petty Caſtles thereabout, and made the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Maſters of above nine hundred Priſoners.</p>
            <p>Upon the 30th the Beſiegers began to play upon the Town with nine Mortars, which ſet it on fire in ſeveral places, though it burnt not very long, the Buildings being all of Stone, and very ſtrong. However, the ſecond Bomb that was thrown kill'd the Lady <hi>Dillon,</hi> and wounded ſeveral others. The next day nine Cannon began to play upon the Caſtle to ruin it, and to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Enemies Communication with their Camp; and the ſame night was erected a Battery of two Mortars more, of eighteen
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48905:17"/>Inches diameter; and ſoon after two more Batteries were finiſh'd, one of fourteen Pieces, the other of ten, all carrying twenty four and eighteen pound Ball. The Report of all the Deſerters, who daily came over to the Leaguer, at that time was, that the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon in the Town was very numerous, but that they were not half arm'd, and that they were in great want of Previſions. But though it is not amiſs for a General to hear what ſuch People ſay, yet there is but little Credit to be given to their Reports, which are moſt frequently fram'd to curry favour. Thus in a few days after, other Deſerters reported, That there were not Proviſions in the Town for many days, and that <hi>d'<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſſone</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, had promiſed to diſmiſs the Militia that were forced in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Town, after the Battel of <hi>Aghrim,</hi> if ſuccour did not come from <hi>France</hi> in twelve days. Of the Truth of all which, an eaſie Conjecture may be made by what has hapned ſince.</p>
            <p>However, after all theſe fair Stories, the General hearing that ſeveral Regiments of the Enemies Horſe, with a Party of <hi>Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parees,</hi> were drawn together in <hi>Kerry,</hi> about ſixteen Miles from <hi>Limerick,</hi> ſent away Brigadier <hi>Leveſon</hi> with five hundred Horſe and Dragoons, in purſuit of the whole Party; who being inform'd of his March, divided themſelves into two Bodies, to make their retreat the more eaſie. Which Brigadier <hi>Leveſon</hi> underſtanding, did the like; and with one part of his Detachment, himſelf pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued one of the Enemies Bodies, while Collonel <hi>Newenhuys</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d the other. Nor was it long before the Brigadier overtook the Party which he purſu'd; and ſo entirely put them to the rout, that very few eſcap'd; among the reſt, the Lord <hi>Caſtle Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi> was taken, and ſent to the Camp with the reſt of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners.</p>
            <p>Upon the 3d of <hi>September,</hi> the Enemies Horſe quitted their Camp, under the Cannon of the Town, and betook themſelves to another that lies in the Road between <hi>Limerick</hi> and <hi>Killalow;</hi> and thus their Horſe being near to ſecond 'em, they poſted four Regiments of Dragoons to guard the Fords of the <hi>Shannon,</hi> in caſe the Enemy ſhould attempt to paſs the River. On the other ſide, the Beſiegers had by this time finiſh'd their Line of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallation, with four Redoubts to defend it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>September</hi> 4. Three hundred Horſe and Dragoons were ſent to re-inforce Brigadier <hi>Leveſon;</hi> who after the Defeat of the two Regiments, and the Body of <hi>Rapparees,</hi> in <hi>Kerry,</hi> was advanc'd farther, in order to the reducing of thoſe few ſmall Garriſons
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48905:18"/>which the <hi>Iriſh</hi> had left in that County; to which purpoſe, is Pieces of Cannon were alſo order'd him for the more ſpeedy ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting his Deſign.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> having put between 2 and 300 of the Proteſtant Inhabitants of <hi>Limerick</hi> into a little Iſland in the <hi>Shannon,</hi> under a ſufficient Guard, their ſad and ſtarving Condition mov'd the Compaſſion of the Officers, to whoſe care they were committed; who being no leſs deſirous themſelves to go over to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſent to Maj. <hi>Stroud,</hi> who then lay poſted with ſome of the <hi>Melitia</hi> not far from the Iſland, to let him underſtand their intentions; upon which, the Major went over with a Party in ſmall Boats; and brought away not only the Guard, but the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, that were almoſt ſtarv'd for want of Food, in a place where they had only two pitiful Hutts to ſhelter them from the Inconveniences of the Weather.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Septemb.</hi> 8. The great Battery of 22 Pieces of Cannon began to play very early in the Morning, and in a ſhort time made a Breach of about 30 yards in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Town, on the North-Eaſt ſide of it. Upon the left of this Battery were alſo planted 8 Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, two of which were 18 Inches in diameter. The next day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the 9th, two more Batteries were finiſh'd, which play'd upon St. <hi>John</hi>'s Gate in the <hi>Iriſh Town.</hi> Theſe Batteries and Mortars playing without intermiſſion, made a world of Havock, diſmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Enemies Cannon, made ſeveral Breaches, ſet the <hi>Engliſh Town</hi> ſeveral times on fire, and laid the greateſt part of it in Rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh; and all this by the 12th at night; at what time ſome of the Beſiegers Bombs falling among the Enemies Stores, burnt three of their Magazines, one of Brandy, and the other two of Bisker, and ſhortly after fired and blew up another Magazine of Powder, which forc'd the Enemy to remove what Proviſions and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition they had left, into the <hi>Iriſh Town.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Septemb.</hi> 15. The Lord <hi>Lisburn</hi> was kill'd by a Cannon Ball, as he was lying upon his Quilt in the Trenches.</p>
            <p>On the 17. One Capt. <hi>Taffe</hi> came over to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and inform'd the General, that the <hi>Engliſh Town</hi> was utterly ruin'd; that the great Guns and Bombs had kill'd a great number of the Garriſon, which at that time was reduc'd to 6000 Foot, and thoſe but very ill clad.</p>
            <p>Upon the <hi>18th.</hi> an Expreſs was ſent to <hi>Dublin</hi> by the Earl of <hi>Granard,</hi> giving this Accompt, that upon his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before <hi>Slego</hi> with a Body of the Army, and Militia of the Country, conſiſting of about 3000 Men, to whom <hi>Baldaric
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48905:18"/>neale,</hi> who was abſolutely come over to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> had joyned his own Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand followers, the Iriſh quitted the Town, and retreated into the Fort; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which his Lordſhip caus'd a Battery to be Rais'd againſt it. But then the Iriſh chuſing rather to ſubmit in time, then ſuffer the fatal Effects of a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Storm, ſurrender'd the Fort upon the <hi>15th.</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> and Marched out accordingly to the Number of between 5 or 600 Men. They left in the Place 16 Pieces of Cannon, 30 Barrels of Powder, more Shot in proportion, and a great Quantity of Proviſion. The Articles they obtain'd were almoſt the ſame with thoſe that were granted to <hi>Galloway,</hi> wherein divers other pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Gariſons were included, upon this Condition that they furrendr'd twenty four Hours after being Summon'd. Much about the ſame time, General <hi>Ginckle</hi> having determined that part of the Army ſhould paſs the <hi>Shannon,</hi> with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to diſſipate or remove the Iriſh Horſe that lay Encamped in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Clare,</hi> and ſhut up the Town on that ſide alſo, the better to conceal his deſign, made a ſhew by giving Orders to draw off and ſhip the heavy Cannon, and quit ſeveral Caſtles near the Camp, as if he intended to raiſe the Siege; which the Enemy believing to be real, expreſſed their joy by loud and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repeated Shouts. But the ſame Night the <hi>Pontons</hi> were laid over the <hi>Shan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> about a Mile above the Town; which was perform'd with that Order and Silence, that upon the <hi>16th.</hi> by break of day, the Royal Regiment of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, with a Detachment both of Horſe and Foot had paſs'd the River be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were diſcover'd by the Enemy. All this while Brigadier <hi>Clifford</hi> lay with four Regiments of Dragoons on the other ſide of the Water, to have hinder'd the <hi>Engliſh</hi> from getting over; and ſo ſoon as he perceiv'd himſelf fruſtrated in his deſign; brought down all his Men on foot (their horſes being at graſs) to make the beſt oppoſition he could. But they were preſently routed, and forc'd to betake themſelves to their Heels, flinging away their Arms, and leaving behind them all their Tents. Baggage, Saddles, Bridles and other Accoutrements, together with two Pieces of Cannon, and the Standard of <hi>Maxwell.</hi> Many were kill'd, and ſeveral taken Priſoners, among whom was a French Lieutenant Collonel. Upon this, the reſt of the Iriſh Horſe, that lay higher up towards <hi>Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lalow,</hi> took the <hi>Alarum,</hi> and drew out as if they had intended ſome ſtout reſiſtance, but as it prov'd, 'twas only to ſecure their Baggage, and get time to take down their Tents. For ſo ſoon as the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> drew near 'em, and had paſs'd the firſt Lane that was between the Iriſh and Them, they March'd off in great diſorder toward the Mountains. Which done, the Horſe return'd to the Camp, and the Foot were poſted at the head of the Bridge. At what time the <hi>Engliſh</hi> alſo took a Caſtle that ſtands in the Middle of the <hi>Shannon,</hi> the Gariſon of which conſiſting of about three-ſcore Men, ſurrender'd at diſcretion; beſides another Poſt not far from it which were of great Uſe to the Beſiegers. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> alſo remov'd their Bridge of Boats nearer to the Town, and ſecur'd two more Paſſes to it, of which one was call'd the Paſs of <hi>Annabegg,</hi> where the <hi>Engliſh</hi> went over the laſt year.</p>
            <p>On the 22d. of <hi>September</hi> the General of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> paſſed the <hi>Shannon</hi> very early in the Morning with a ſtrong Party of Horſe and Dragoons, and Ten Regiments of Infantry, and fourteen Pieces of Cannon, leaving the reſt of the Army under the Command of the Duke of <hi>Wittenbergh</hi> to ſecure the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers Works on the other ſide of the River. About Noon the ſame day, both Horſe and Foot were drawn up before the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Town, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Enemy play'd upon 'em all the while from the Caſtle, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Towers, both with their great Guns and ſmall Shot. About four of the Clock in the Afternoon, the General Order'd all the Granadeers together with the Regiments of Collonel <hi>Kirk,</hi> Collonel <hi>Yiffin,</hi> and the Lord <hi>George Hamilton</hi> to Advance and Attack the Fort that ſecures <hi>Thomend</hi> Bridge; at what time the Beſieged ſent two great Detachments out of the Town, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inforce
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48905:19"/>and ſecond their own Party that defended it. But notwithſtanding all this, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> went on with that Courage and Bravery, that they beat the Enemy from their Works, who thereupon fled to the Town in hopes to have been let in. But the Governour fearing leaſt the Victorious <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhould have Enter'd with the fugitives, durſt not let down the draw Bridge to receive them, which occaſion'd a great ſlaughter of the vanquiſh'd Iriſh, ſo that nothing was to be ſeen from the foot or <hi>Thomond</hi> Bridge to the draw Bridge, but heaps of dead Bodies. Six hundred of the Enemy were ſlain, and about one handred and thirty raken Priſoners, among which Number was Collonel <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kelton</hi> (ſince dead of his wounds) two Lieutenant Collonels, two Majors, three Captains, ſeven Lieutenants and ſix Enſigns. The loſs which the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> ſuſtain'd was occaſion'd more by their own Contempt of Danger, and too eager purſuit of Victory, than the Reſiſtance of the Enemy. For all the while the conflict endur'd, the Enemy play'd with their Great and Small Shot from the Walls of the Town at a more than ordinary Rate: which was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that the Mettle of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> precipitating them too far, they were much more than they needed to have been, expos'd to the Enemies Fire: ſo that between two and three hundred were ſlain and wounded, tho not any one of Remark.</p>
            <p>The next day in the Afternoon the Gariſon beat a Parley on both ſides of the <hi>River,</hi> and deſir'd a Truce, which was agreed upon by the General; which time being expir'd, <hi>Sarsfield</hi> and <hi>Wahop</hi> came forth, and deſir'd the Truce might be continu'd for three days, to the End they might ſend to their Horſe, which lay toward <hi>Clare,</hi> to know upon what Conditions they expected to be comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Capitulation.</p>
            <p>Upon the <hi>25th.</hi> Collonel <hi>Sheldon,</hi> and ſome other of the Enemies Officers came into the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Camp, and thence went into <hi>Limerick.</hi> The next Day <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rsfield</hi> and <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hop</hi> din'd with the General; and the Lord <hi>Cutts,</hi> Sir <hi>David Collier,</hi> Collonel <hi>Tiffany</hi> and Collonel <hi>Fiper</hi> were ſent as Hoſtages into the Town, and the Lords <hi>Weſtmeath, lveagh, Trimbleſtown</hi> and <hi>Lowth,</hi> remain'd in the Camp as Hoſtages for the Gariſon. Upon the <hi>27th.</hi> the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſent out their Propoſals, which the General not approving, inſtead of an Anſwer, ſent back twelve other Articles, which was all he would allow them; and at the ſame time gave Orders for the great Guns and Mortars to be in a rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>neſs, in caſe they reſas'd the Propoſals he had ſent; which brought down the Stomac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who ſeeing the Reſolution of the General and finding to other Remedy, at length, upon the third of this Month came to a final Concluſion, ſo that the Articles of Capitulation were ſigned the ſame Day, conſiſting of two Parts, the one relating to Civil Affairs, which were ſigned by the Lords Juſtices, the General, and the Perſons deputed by the Garri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on; and the other in reference to the Military Affairs, which were ſubſcribed by the Generals on both Sides, Such of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> as have a Mind to paſs the Seas, are to have the Liberty, for their preſent Convenience, to ſtay in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Town and the Iſland, till they can be ſhip'd away. And the Caſtles of <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> and <hi>Clare,</hi> together with all other Places and Caſtles that as yet are in the Poſſeſſion of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> are by Vertue of the ſame Capitulation, to be forth with deliver'd up to the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> So that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urrender of this Town complents the Conqueſt of the whole Kingdom of <hi>Ireland.</hi> In purſuance of the Agreement, one Gate of the Town was delivered up that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vening; it being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> late t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> march into the Town; but the next Day the <hi>Iriſh</hi> being quite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> out, the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in and took Poſſeſſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it with ſeven Reginments of Font. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome others, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> deſign to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>French</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> themſelves the more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> up ſome of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>French</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to go along with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> may our next Journal attend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48905:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
